<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>AspectWerkz</title>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Features">

            <subsection name="AspectWerkz supports the following features">
                <p>
                    This is a very incomplete list, see the documentation for all features.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Runtime and load time bytecode modification (weaving).
                        Hooks in and transforms classes loaded by
                        <b>any</b> class loader
                        except the bootstrap class loader. Which basically means that
                        you can easily transform any (legacy) application or external
                        library apart from rt.jar both at runtime and compile time.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        The join point model supports: method execution and call, constructor execution and call,
                        field access, field modification, catch handlers and cflow. All advice works with all join points.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Introductions (Mixins/Open Classes), i.e. the possibility
                        to add interfaces and implementations to existing classes.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Attributes definition. Define your aspects using runtime attributes (ready for JSR-175).
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        XML definition. Define your aspects using XML. The XML definition can also be used to refine,
                        override and resolve the attribute definition.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Four different deployment models (scope) for both advices
                        and introductions: perJVM (singleton), perClass, perInstance
                        and perThread.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Hot deployment, advices and introductions can be
                        dynamically deployed, undeployed or rearranged (without
                        reloading or retransforming the target classes).
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Very high-performant. An
                        <code>advice</code> adds an overhead of only ~0.000009 ms/call
                        (on my Intel Pentium 4 Mobile 1.6 Mhz).
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Fine-grained pattern language for selecting the join points.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Highly orthogonal underlying model. All advice works with all join points and pointcut composition
                        supports mixing all kinds of pointcuts. Largely inspired by AspectJ.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        "Offline" transformation (can be used as a post-processor).
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Aspects, advices and introductions are written in plain old
                        Java code. I.e. no new language to learn, no new compilation
                        phases, no need to tell your manager ;-)
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        The target classes can be regular POJOs (Plain Old Java
                        Objects), i.e. do not need to have an interface.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Support for passing parameters to the advices through
                        the definition and for defining advice stacks which can
                        be reused.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <!--                    <li>-->
                    <!--                        Multiple AspectWerkz systems can be used in the same JVM concurrently.-->
                    <!--                    </li>-->
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Meta-data additions to classes. Possibilities to add meta-data to all loaded classes.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        Simple usage and configuration.
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>

