<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Releases</title>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
        <author email="alex at gnilux dot com">alexandre vasseur</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Official Builds">
            <subsection name="Releases">
                <p>
                    The latest official release is 1.0
                </p>
                <p>
                    Download:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <a href="http://dist.codehaus.org/aspectwerkz/distributions/aspectwerkz-1.0.zip?download">1.0</a>
                        </li>
                        <br/>
                        <li>
                            <a href="http://dist.codehaus.org/aspectwerkz/distributions/aspectwerkz-0.10.zip?download">0.10</a>
                        </li>
                        <br/>
                        <li>
                            <a href="http://dist.codehaus.org/aspectwerkz/distributions/aspectwerkz-0.9.zip?download">0.9</a>
                        </li>
                        <br/>
                        <li>
                            <a href="http://dist.codehaus.org/aspectwerkz/distributions/aspectwerkz-0.8.1.zip?download">0.8.1</a>
                        </li>
                        <br/>
                        <li>
                            <a href="http://aspectwerkz.codehaus.org/downloads/">Native HotSwap modules (for 0.8 and later).</a>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <section name="Release notes">
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0">
                    <p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>AnnotationCTask to run AnnotaionC annotation compiler from Ant as a custom task
                            (thanks to the_mindstorm(at)evolva(dot)ro)</li>
                            <li>AspectWerkzCTask to run AspectWerkzC offline weaving from Ant as a custom task
                            (thanks to the_mindstorm(at)evolva(dot)ro)</li>
                            <li>Minor bug fix when using META-INF/aop.xml in J2EE environments</li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0.RC3">
                    <p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Bug fix in Annotation matching when using offline mode weaving. Thanks to Allan Jones.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Bug fix in handler join point when Rtti is used.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                ASM jars are now remapped and embedded in aspectwerkz-<i>version</i>.jar so that it
                                is possible to use AspectWerkz within projects having a dependancy on a specific
                                ASM version (e.g. cglib, Hibernate, Spring, Geronimo, etc).<br/>
                                The bin/aspectwerkz scripts are thus not referencing ASM anymore. ASM is only used
                                if you need to recompile the project or when doing framework debugging.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                New sample for annotation matching (ant samples:annotation, ant samples:offline:annotation)
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0.RC2">
                    <p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Better support for complex custom annotations, less requirements when writing the annotation proxy.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Fix in pointcut matching that lead to a slow weave time behavior in 1.0.RC1
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Fixed an issue when using the join point RTTI in multi threaded environments or in case of reentrancy
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Upgraded Javassist dependancy from 3.0beta to 3.0RC1
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Upgraded to ASM 1.5.1
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Removed piccolo.jar from the <code>bin/</code> scripts since it is only required for Java 1.3 or JRockit (see FAQ, especially for use with WebLogic)
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Other bug fixes
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0.RC1">
                    <p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Support for <b>args()</b> in the pointcut expressions. As a consequence, support for
                                direct access to arguments of advised method is possible and advices can have those
                                parameters in their signature. See <a href="definition_issues.html#Pointcut_definition">docs</a>.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <code>hasmethod</code> and
                                <code>hasfield</code> pointcuts (contributed by <a href="http://today.java.net/pub/au/80">Michael Nascimento Santos</a>)
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                J2SE 5 JVMTI (JSR-163) support updated for latest specification.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                bin/aspectwerkz command line tool now provides autodetection of BEA JRockit and J2SE 5.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Support for pointcut expression defined in the XML body of the &lt;pointcut&gt; element.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                 Bug fixes.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0-beta2">
                    <p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
						   		Many bug fixes.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 1.0-beta1">
                    <p>
                        Amont many other things this release is shipped with a completely new pointcut grammar which is much more
                        expressive and powerful, and rich annotation support for both typed and untyped annotations.
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Support for deploying several
                                <code>aop.xml</code> Aspect defintion/deployment files alongside deployed
                                application (
                                <code>WEB-INF/aop.xml</code>,
                                <code>META-INF/aop.xml</code>) and have them following
                                the classloader hierarchy.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                One single API to access both JavaDoc-style and Java 1.5 annotations, allows using them
                                together seamlessly.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Typed and untyped annotations for JavaDoc-style annotations.
                                Supports the same parameters types as Java 1.5 annotations and has strongly
                                typed compile time checking (using a new annotation compiler).
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <code>within</code> and
                                <code>withincode</code> pointcuts
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                More expressive
                                <code>cflow</code> pointcuts that can take any pointcut
                                expression as "parameter" and can be used to build arbitrary nested expressions.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Matching on annotations.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Matching on modifiers (including
                                <code>!public</code> and
                                <code>NOT static</code> etc.)
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Matching on subtypes for parameters and return values.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                System wide pointcuts (in the XML deployment descriptor).
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Pointcut references (refer to pointcuts defined in other aspects than the one you are using it in).
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                JSR-163 JVMTI support for Java 1.5 class load time weaving with
                                <code>-javaagent:</code>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                JoinPoint class is now serializable.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                JoinPoint instances can be "resetted", to start over a complete advice chain (useful for failover etc.).
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Documentation enhanced and refactored.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Introductory tutorials.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Some bug fixes.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Please note that there are changes to the way annotations (formerly call attributes)
                                are complied and retrieved. F.e.
                                <code>AspectC</code> has been replaced by
                                <code>AnnontationC</code>
                                and has slightly different options, so to compile the aspects use
                                <code>AnnotationC</code>
                                from now on.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.10">
                    <p>
                        This release is mainly a bug-fix release. Refer to release note of 0.10.RC2 and 0.10.RC1 for a list of new
                        features as compared to 0.9.
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                A thread safe issue has been fixed in the join point execution model.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                IBM JRE support has been fixed.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Unix/Linux comamnd line scripts has been fixed (was missing bcel.jar).
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Exception throwned by method of weaved classes are not wrapped anymore. Exception throwned
                                by mixin implementation are not wrapped anymore.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                JIT
                                <code>JoinPoint</code> compilation is now thread safe.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <code>serialVersionUID</code> computation fixed.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                Due to a lack of
                                <code>within</code> expression support in the pointcut grammar (addressed in 1.0), the handler pointcut
                                are very expensive to match. Those are deactivated by default. If your system uses those handler pointcuts, you have to
                                add the
                                <code>-Daspectwerkz.handler.pointcut=true</code> JVM option when starting up your JVM.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.10RC2">
                    <p>
                        In this release is mainly a bug-fix release, but we have added some new functionality
                        (and changed some APIs) as well:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Aspects does not have to extend the
                                <code>Aspect</code> base class anymore, but
                                can be any Java class and extend anything they like.
                            </li>
                            <br/>
                            <li>
                                The
                                <code>JoinPoint</code> class has these two methods:
                                <ul>
                                    <li>
                                        <code>getSignature()</code> - which is used to retrieve the static signature
                                        for the join point.
                                    </li>
                                    <li>
                                        <code>getRtti()</code> - which is used to retrieve the RTTI (Runtime Type Information)
                                        about the join point.
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                                Both these methods returns a base interface that could be used, but is usually best
                                to cast to a more fine-grained and specific type.
                            </li>
                            <br/>
                            <li>
                                Retrieval of information about the system, adding and reading of parameters and metadata etc. is
                                done through the
                                <code>CrossCuttingInfo</code> class. An aspect or mixin that is
                                interested in accessing this info should have a constructor that takes a
                                <code>CrossCuttingInfo</code> instance as its only parameter.
                                See the docs for details.
                            </li>
                            <br/>
                            <li>
                                Pluggable aspect container - The possibility to provide your own aspect container
                                implementation is back.
                                Useful if you need to control how your aspects are instantiated for example if you
                                want that to be handled by an IoC container (Spring, PicoContainer etc.))
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.10RC1">
                    <p>
                        AspectWerkz has gone through a lot of changes, the whole core engine has
                        for example been thrown out and replaced by a much more flexible and
                        performant one.  The join point model is much more expressive and
                        orthogonal we have also implemented a JIT compiler that is making
                        AspectWerkz much more performant.  On top of that we have a new
                        implementation of true runtime weaving, which allows you to redefine
                        your aspect model including adding
                        <b>new</b> pointcuts at runtime.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        We will not list all new features here, see the
                        <a href="http://aspectwerkz.codehaus.org/">docs</a>
                        for details. But the main new features are these:
                    </p>
                    <subsection name="Expressiveness and orthogonality">
                        <p>
                            We have improved the expressiveness and orthogonality a lot.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            AspectWerkz currently supports the following join points:
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    method (static and member) execution
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    method (static and member) call
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    constructor execution
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    constructor call
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    field (static and member) modification
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    field (static and member) access
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    catch clauses
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    cflow
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            In the latest version we have reached a high level of orthogonality:
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    All advice types (around, after and before) works with all poincut
                                    designators (except for the handler pointcut which is only possible to
                                    bind to the before advice).
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    You can compose new pointcuts by mixing any types of pointcuts.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                            The syntax has changed slightly, both in the XML and annotation definition. However not more than that the migration should be fairly easy. See the
                            <a href="http://aspectwerkz.codehaus.org/">docs</a> for details on the new syntax.
                        </p>
                    </subsection>
                    <subsection name="Performance improvements and JIT compilation">
                        <p>
                        We have implemented a JIT (Just-In-Time) compiler that detects advice chains that are often
                        executed and generates a custom class on the fly that invokes the advice chain
                        and the target join point statically.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                        Here are some simple but interesting benchmarks comparing the latest distribution of
                        AspectWerkz, JBoss and AspectJ:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <b>The overhead of one around advice applied to a method call join point:</b>
                            <table>
                                <tr>
                                    <th></th>
                                    <th></th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>AspectJ 1.1.1
                                    </td>
                                    <td>0.000018 ms/call
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>AspectWerkz 0.10 RC1
                                    </td>
                                    <td>0.000097 ms/call
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>JBoss AOP 1.0Beta
                                    </td>
                                    <td>0.000181 ms/call
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                            </table>
                        </p>
                    </subsection>
                    <subsection name="Runtime weaving">
                        <p>
                        In addition to the capabilities to rearrange aspects and advices at existing
                        join points and swapping mixin implementation
                        at runtime, we provide a unique feature of adding new pointcuts at runtime
                        without any prior knowledge.
                        The implementation is based on Java HotSwap and thus requires a compliant
                        JVM.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                        A simple API allows to refine the aspect definition to add new pointcuts
                        and then trigger the activation of it.  Prior to pointcuts addition,
                        your programs are guaranteed to run without any overhead since the
                        bytecode does not gets modified prior activation. Moreover the runtime
                        weaving does not require to have a remote JVM to control the HotSwap
                        API since we provide a dedicated in-process module.
                        </p>
                    </subsection>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.9.x">
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Online architecture for class load time weaving supports IBM JRE and BEA JRockit
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            DTD has been refactored to support
                            <code>system</code> element and deprecated syntax from 0.8.x has been removed
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            New self-defined / self-contained Aspect model based on metadata / JSR-175 concepts.
                            The new Aspect model coexists with the 0.former model and both will be maintained since they
                            target different needs
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            New pointcut algebra implementation
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Released under LGPL-style license
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Documentation reorganized for new Aspect model coverage
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Bug fix (refer to
                            <a href="http://jira.codehaus.org/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10105">Jira</a>)
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.8.x">
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            JDK 1.3 compatible.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            New online architecture, with several options and java 1.3 support
                            (not dependent on JMangler anymore).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            New annotations -> XML compiler (no more metaData dir and meta-data
                            compilers)
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Offline compiler refactored. Now support rollback on error facility.
                            (Note that the
                            <code>bin/aspectwerkz -offline</code> must now
                            be invocated with the definition file as first argument.)
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Documentation updated and reorganized.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Released under a BSD-style license.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Tested and verified to work for EJBs under WLS using both online
                            and offline mode.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Non-reentrancy configuration for join points.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Definition validator.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.7.x">
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Pluggable custom defined join point controller. The
                            join point controller gives you complete control
                            over your advices at runtime (at certain join
                            points).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Package namespaces and scopes in the XML definition.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            cflow (control flow) pointcuts.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Performance improvement for advices by a factor of 2.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Many, many bugfixes (introduced by the new pointcut model
                            implementation in 0.6.x).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            The runtime annotations tags have changed. (They now have
                            an aspectwerkz namespace and are using the same syntax as XDoclet.)
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            The prefix
                            <code>___AW_</code> is now used at all introduced methods and fields.
                            Including the
                            <code>Identifiable.getUuid</code> method which is renamed to
                            <code>___AW_getUuid</code>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Documentation and examples have been updated.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Uses new version of JMangler (3.0.2) which is released under LGPL.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.6.x">
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Completely new definition model. Aspects, advices,
                            introductions and pointcuts are now completely orthogonal
                            and the model now has the essence of the AspectJ model.
                            See the documentation for details.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Abstract aspects definitions as well as pointcut expressions
                            (e.g.
                            <code>((pc1 OR pc2) AND !pc3)</code> and similar).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Multiple weave models.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Multiple AspectWerkz system can run in the same JVM concurrently.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            setField and getField now works for get and set java.util.*
                            collection fields (e.g. add/get/remove/size and so on).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Advice and introduction container is now pluggable. I.e. the
                            user can provide its own custom implementation (f.e. to enable
                            persistence).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            The transparent persistence of advices and introductions have
                            been moved to the sandbox.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Many bug fixes.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="New features and changes in release 0.5.x">
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Caller side pointcuts. I.e. the possibility to advise a
                            method invocation (caller side) apart from method
                            execution (callee side).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Fine-grained pattern language for picking out pointcuts.
                            It is now possible to pick out method pointcuts by method name,
                            parameter types and return type as well as field pointcuts
                            by field name and field type. All these support regular
                            expressions.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Runtime attributes for advices (method/field/throws).
                            I.e. add meta-data to your methods/field/classes as
                            JavaDoc tags which are picked up by the weaver and
                            used as rule set when doing the transformations.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Class selectors for aspects. I.e. pick out classes using
                            regular expressions.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Advising of static fields.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Parameters to advices. The possibility to pass
                            parameters to advices through the XML definition.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Advice stacks. The possibility to define stacks/chains
                            of advices that can be reused throughout the XML definition.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            MethodAdvice has been renamed to AroundAdvice and the
                            FieldAdvices has been renamed to PreAdvice and PostAdvice.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Creation and registration of new advices at runtime
                            (in previous releases you could only add/remove/reorder
                            existing advices).
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Ant task for offline post-processing.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            More flexible startup and definition handling process.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Multiple pattern declarations for pointcuts.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            More documentation and examples.
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Many many bugfixes.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

